<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Lords spiritual and temporal, in the Abby-church at Westminster, on the 5th of November, 1696 being the anniversary thanksgiving, for the happy deliverance from the gunpowder treason : and also, for the happy arrival of His Present Majesty on this day, for the deliverance of our church and nation / by ... Symon Lord Bishop of Ely.</title>
            <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22926</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12745149</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12745149</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56707)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 727:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Lords spiritual and temporal, in the Abby-church at Westminster, on the 5th of November, 1696 being the anniversary thanksgiving, for the happy deliverance from the gunpowder treason : and also, for the happy arrival of His Present Majesty on this day, for the deliverance of our church and nation / by ... Symon Lord Bishop of Ely.</title>
                  <author>Patrick, Simon, 1626-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A thanksgiving sermon before the Lords.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Daniel IV, 35 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the <hi>Lords Spiritual and Temporal,</hi> IN THE ABBY-CHURCH at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> On the <hi>5th</hi> of <hi>November,</hi> 1696. BEING THE Anniverſary Thankſgiving, For the happy Deliverance from the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon.</hi> AND ALSO, For the happy Arrival of His preſent MAJESTY on this Day, for the Deliverance of our CHURCH and NATION.</p>
            <p>By the Right Reverend Father in God, SYMON Lord Biſhop of ELY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, M DC XC VI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93238:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93238:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED Before the LORDS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IV. DANIEL 35.</bibl>
               <q>—<hi>And he doth according to his will, in the army of heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth: and none can stay his hand, or ſay unto him, what doſt thou?</hi>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HESE Words are part of a Pious <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> which King <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> ſet forth, unto all People, Nations, and Languages, <hi>to ſhew</hi> (as he ſaith in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to it, <hi>ver.</hi> 2.) <hi>the ſigns and the wonders which the high God had wrought toward him.</hi> Which hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing profoundly admired and adored in the next words, <hi>v.</hi> 3. [<hi>How great are his ſigns, and how mighty are his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi>]
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:93238:3"/> he proceeds to give the World an account, what an amazing turn there had lately been in his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. For, when he was lifted up to the higheſt pitch of Princely Power and Glory, and had nothing to fear on Earth; he was admoniſhed from Heaven in a Dream, of his ſudden fall into a condition as low as the Beaſts: In which he was to remain, till he ſhould be made ſenſible, <hi>That the moſt high ruleth in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of men and giveth it to whom ſoever he will,</hi> v. 17. Accordingly he relates how all this, not long after, came to paſs. The effect of which was, that it took down his Pride, (for which ſo great an abaſement was the moſt proper remedy) and brought him to a ſober ſenſe, that God governs the World; and orders all things every where by his Over-ruling Providence; with an Abſolute Power, which none can withſtand or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Which is a Meditation very ſeaſonable at this time, when we are met together to commemorate the Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Providence of God over us in this Church and Kingdom, upon a double account. <hi>Firſt,</hi> In Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and Defeating one of the deepeſt and moſt deſperate Conſpiracies againſt us, that ever was hatcht in Hell: <hi>Secondly,</hi> In diſappointing the ſame reſtleſs Enemies again; when by their Fraud and our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they had contrived themſelves into ſuch an height of Power, that we had no means left to preſerve our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Liberties.</p>
            <p>Had we no other Arguments of the Over-ruling Power of Gods Eternal Providence in the World, but theſe and ſuch as theſe; they might be ſufficient to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken the ſenſe of it in your minds; and to make us
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93238:3"/> conclude, That <hi>He doth according to his will in the army of Heaven, and among the inhabitants of the earth: and none can ſtay his hand, or ſay unto him, What doſt thou?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In treating of which Words, I ſhall only conſider theſe Two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Extent of God's Sovereign Dominion and Government.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Way and Method whereby he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>I. For the <hi>firſt</hi> of theſe, my Text reſolves us, that there is nothing exempt from it; but it reaches to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Creature throughout the whole World: which are comprehended in theſe Words, <hi>The army of heaven, and the inhabitants of the earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the former of which, the <hi>Army,</hi> or <hi>Hoſt</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Holy Scriptures are wont to expreſs, both thoſe Beings in the Heaven, that are <hi>Inviſible,</hi> and thoſe that are <hi>Viſible, Viz.</hi> the Angels; and the Sun, Moon and Stars. Both theſe are called the <hi>Hoſt of Heaven;</hi> and with reſpect to both God is ſtiled, the <hi>LORD of Hoſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us look with our minds into the <hi>Inviſible</hi> World: The World of Spirits, both good and bad. For, that there are ſuch Beings hath been the Senſe of all Mankind, in all Ages, (as it were eaſie to ſhew, if this were a place proper for it) but the Holy Scriptures have given us the cleareſt and fulleſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93238:4"/> account of them; not only informing us, but giving us particular Inſtances, how God rules and Governs them with an abſolute Authority: The good Angels obeying his Voice, and the Devils trembling at his Preſence. That is, he governs the good by his Will; and he reſtrains the evil by his Almighty Power. The good chearfully perform his Pleaſure; and the evil are conſtrained to do it: Being made to ſerve the ends of his Wiſe Providence, where they deſign to gratifie their own malice.</p>
               <p>Out of thoſe Sacred Records therefore, I ſhall briefly lay before you the devout ſenſe which the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Perſons have had of the extent of God's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; without entring into the other evident proofs we have of this Doctrine.</p>
               <p>Read then, and conſider thoſe words of the Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> (CIII. 20.) and they will inform you how God governs the Holy Angels. <hi>Bleſs the LORD, ye Angels that excel in ſtrength, that do his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, hearkening to the voice of his words. Bleſs the LORD all ye his Hoſts, ye Miniſters of his that do his pleaſure.</hi> The like you read, in the very next <hi>Pſalm</hi> CIV. 4. <hi>He maketh his Angels Spirits; his Miniſter is a flaming fire.</hi> For, ſo did the Angels ſometimes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; in a glittering and ſhining manner, like a flame of fire.</p>
               <p>And hence it is, that they are ſtiled <hi>The Chariots of God;</hi> becauſe they are an Hoſt or Army to execute his Will and Pleaſure, <hi>Pſal.</hi> LXVIH. 17. <hi>The Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots of God are twenty thouſand, even thouſands of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: the LORD is among them, as in Sinai, &amp;c.</hi> And hence alſo they are ſaid, more particularly, to be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93238:4"/> 
                  <hi>Miniſtring Spirits ſet forth to Miniſter, for them who ſhall be Heirs of Salvation,</hi> 1 Hebr. ult. That is, they Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter to the Will of God, for the preſervation and ſafety of good Chriſtians: unto whom God deſigns a happineſs beyond this World, in his heavenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and therefore will not let them want his care of them, while they continue here.</p>
               <p>And in like manner the ſame Soveraignty of God is repreſented in Holy Scripture, as Governing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils alſo: whom he aws and reſtrains by his Power. For, when he caſt them out of Heaven, for their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt him, <hi>he delivered them into Chains of Darkneſs, to be reſerved unto Judgment,</hi> 2 Pet. 11. 4. This Judgment they expect, and tremble at the Thoughts of it; becauſe they know they cannot avoid it: and thence are ſaid, <hi>to believe and tremble,</hi> 2 Jam. 19. And they expect it in <hi>Chains;</hi> feel, that is, the Power of God upon them, tying them up and reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; ſo that they cannot do what, nor go whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they pleaſe: but are like great Malefactors, who till they are brought before the Judge, are bound in Chains, and cannot ſtir; but whether their Keeper thinks fit to ſuffer them.</p>
               <p>Thus we find they were perfectly ſubject to our Bleſſed Saviour; and by him, to thoſe whom he ſent to Preach the Goſpel: who at their return came and told him, <hi>Lord, even the Devils are ſubject to us, through thy Name,</hi> 10 Luke 17. They fled, when they did but hear of him; they quitted their Poſſeſſion when his Power approached: they were not able to ſtand before his Authority. Which is ſufficient to ſhew how God Rules the Inviſible World, in every part of it: over all the Hoſts of Angels and Legions of Devils, who cannot reſiſt his Word.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93238:5"/>
               <p>And now if we lift up our Eyes unto the Viſible Heaven, we behold there another <hi>Army,</hi> the Sun, Moon, and Stars, run<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ing the Courſe that God hath appointed them; and we read alſo of their ſtanding ſtill at his Commandment. For, <hi>he bringeth the Sun as a Bridegroom out of his Chamber,</hi> (ſaith the Pſalmiſt) <hi>and it rejoyceth as a ſtrong young Man to run a Race,</hi> XIX. 5. But if he pleaſes, he can ſtop its Courſe, and hinder its Motion; as he did in the Days of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>Sun, ſtand thou ſtill upon Gibeon, and thou Moon in the Vally of Ajalon. And the Sun ſtood ſtill, and the Moon ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, until the People had avenged themſelves upon their Enemies,</hi> X. Joſh. 12, 13. The <hi>Stars</hi> alſo are ſaid to have <hi>fought in their Courſes against Siſara,</hi> V. Judg. 20, by powring out, perhaps, ſome violent Storm upon him: which diſcomfited his numerous Army, and broke their Ranks, and put them into ſuch Diſorder, that it was apparent Heaven fought againſt them.</p>
               <p>And accordingly the <hi>Thunder,</hi> which is ſaid alſo to come out of Heaven, is called the <hi>Voice of God,</hi> (XXIX. Pſal. 5, 7, 8.) who is ſaid alſo in the firſt Leſſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for this Day (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> XXII. 14. 15.) to ſhoot out <hi>Lightning,</hi> like Arrows; whereby <hi>David</hi>'s Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were ſcattered. The <hi>Clouds</hi> of Heaven, likewiſe he is ſaid in other places, <hi>to make his Chariot,</hi> (CIV. Pſal. 3.) <hi>and to walk upon the Wings of the Wind:</hi> becauſe he hath often employed thoſe in terrible Blaſts, and furious Tempeſts, of Rain, and Hail, and ſtormy Winds; which as the Pſalmiſt elſewhere ſays, fulfil his Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>II. And now if we bring our Thoughts down from the upper Regions of the World, unto theſe lower,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93238:5"/> wherein we live, we have the ſame devout Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments of all good Men, that he hath an abſolute Dominion there; and doth according to his Will <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Inhabitants of the Earth,</hi> as well as in <hi>the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of Heaven.</hi> For, the <hi>Earth</hi> it ſelf is ſaid to tremble and ſhake before him, (2 <hi>Sam.</hi> XXII. 8. CIV. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.) as it did at the giving of the Law from Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> and at other times. <hi>He Ruleth alſo the Raging of the Sea: when the Waves thereof ariſe, he ſtilleth them,</hi> LXXXIX. Pſal. 9. Nor is his Dominion limited to inanimate Creatures, but extends alſo to <hi>every living thing, to whom he opens his Hand, and ſatisfies their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,</hi> CXLV. Pſal. 16. But the principal <hi>Inhabitants of the Earth</hi> are Mankind; to whom he hath given Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over all other Creatures, (I. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.) and Rules over Men, as Men Rule over other things. <hi>For, he turneth Man to Deſtruction, and ſayeth, Return ye Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Men,</hi> XC. Pſal. 3. He lifts up, and caſts down according to his Pleaſure. He ſets up one and puts down another: for, he is the Judge; whoſe Sentence none can reverſe.</p>
               <p>Nor doth he Rule over Mens outward Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments only; but ſways their Minds, and moves and influences their Hearts. For, <hi>the preparation of the Heart of Man, and the anſwer of the Tongue is from the LORD,</hi> XVI. Prov. 1.</p>
               <p>Which is true, not only of mean Perſons; Men of low Degree, of eaſie and flexible Minds: but of the higheſt and mightieſt Orders; of the ſtouteſt and moſt undaunted Spirits; of Kings and Princes, of their great Captains and Commanders, their wiſe Counſellers, and deep Stateſmen, whom he frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infatuates, and brings their Councels to nought,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93238:6"/> when they croſs his Will. For, with him is both <hi>Strength and Wiſdom,</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> admirably ſpeaks) <hi>he lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Counſellers away ſpoiled, and maketh the Judges fools. He leadeth Princes away ſpoiled, and overthroweth the mighty. He removeth away the Speech of the Truſty, and taketh away the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding of the Aged. He powreth Contempt upon Princes, and weakneth the Strength of the Mighty,</hi> XII. Job. 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This was the Senſe of that Holy Man in the moſt ancient Times; and Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity made the ſame Obſervations. For, <hi>many Kings</hi> (ſaith the Son of <hi>Sirach) have ſet down upon the Ground; and one that was never thought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of hath worn the Crown. Many mighty Men have been greatly diſgraced: and the Honourable delivered into other mens Hands,</hi> XI. Eccluſ. 5. 6.</p>
               <p>Nor, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> doth he Govern ſingle Perſons only; but Kingdoms alſo, and the greateſt Societies of Men. From whence he is called <hi>the God of all the Kingdoms of the Earth,</hi> 2 Kings XIX. 15. and ſaid to <hi>Rule over all the Kingdoms of the Heathen,</hi> (as well as over his People <hi>Iſrael</hi>) with ſuch a <hi>Power and Might, as none is able to withſtand,</hi> 2 Chron. XX. 6.</p>
               <p>Thus I have as briefly as I could, repreſented the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of God's Dominion and Providence; which Rules over the whole World, Viſible and Inviſible: reaching to all things in Heaven, and to all in Earth; to all and every Creature, and to all the Concerns of every one of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>I proceed now to the <hi>Second</hi> thing I undertook, which is to ſhow the Way and Method of this Divine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93238:6"/> Government: whereby it will appear, that all this that I have Reported from the Holy Scripture, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently true; and cannot be denied by thoſe who believe God to be the Creator of Heaven and of Earth.</p>
               <p>And here I ſhall conſider only theſe <hi>Four</hi> things,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>First,</hi> That God ſees and knows all things through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That nothing can come to paſs, but what he either effects or permits.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He effects and permits nothing, but for wiſe and worthy Ends. And</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He certainly accompliſhes theſe Ends, and that by ſuch Means as he pleaſes.</item>
               </list>
               <p>I. <hi>First,</hi> I ſay, God ſees and knows all Things, all Perſons, and whatſoever appertains unto them; and that in all poſſible Meaſures, in Meaſures Infinite and Incomprehenſible by us: but which we are ſure to be true, becauſe he made and formed all Things; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt be privy to every Motion which it is poſſible for them to have, and is preſent to every the ſmalleſt Inclination they make to any Motion. He knows their Nature; he underſtands the Vertue of every Cauſe; he perfectly comprehends what it can do, and how far it can go; he diſcerns its Intentions, and what it deſigns: Nothing can be concealed from him, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing lies naked, bare, and open before him. For, <hi>the Eyes of the LORD,</hi> ſaith his Prophet, <hi>run to and fro throughout the whole Earth,</hi> 2 Chron. XVI. 9. that is, his Knowledge comprehends all things, every-where.</p>
               <p>And as for Man, <hi>his Ways are before the Eyes of the LORD, and he pondereth all his goings,</hi> (V. Prov. 21.)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93238:7"/> for <hi>his Eyes are in every Place, beholding the Evil and the Good,</hi> XV. Prov. 3.</p>
               <p>Nor are his outward Actions only expoſed to him; but all the Thoughts and Deſigns of his Heart: For, <hi>Hell and Deſtruction are before the LORD: how much more then the Hearts of the Children of Men?</hi> XV. Prov. 11. The moſt ſecret Imaginations of their Minds, the deepeſt Deſires of their Souls, all the Windings and Turnings of their Spirits, in their moſt retired Conſultations; even thoſe Motions which are not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by themſelves, are all known to God. Whence thoſe Expreſſions in the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> XVII. 10. <hi>I the LORD ſearch the Heart, and try the Reins, even to give to every Man according to his Ways, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the fruit of his Doings.</hi> And in the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> XI. 5. <hi>Thus ſaith the LORD, thus have ye ſaid, O Houſe of Iſrael: for, I know the things that come into your Mind, every one of them.</hi> Which declare, that God doth not only ſee and know what is ſubject to outward View; but the very Thoughts of mens Hearts alſo: yea, and every one of thoſe Thoughts, and the Entrance or Beginning of them.</p>
               <p>II. But further, as he infallibly knows all things, ſo nothing comes to paſs, but what he either effects or permits: and permits, not becauſe he cannot, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not pleaſed to hinder it; for, he Acts every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <hi>according to his Will.</hi> There is a Providence in all things under his Government; but there is a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the Exerciſe of it. That which is good and worthy of God in the Mind, and Counſels, and Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Men, that may and ought to be aſcribed to God, and to his Grace; as guiding, aiding, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93238:7"/> therein. But that which is wicked in them, muſt not be thus aſcribed to him; as if he moved or excited them to it, (for, he cannot will any thing that is Evil) but only that he did permit it, when he could have hindred it: for the Accompliſhment of ſuch Ends, as thoſe wicked Agents did not think of. In both theſe are the clear Lines of Providence; though in different Characters.</p>
               <p>For, how often do we Read of God's Working, what he pleaſes throughout the World? particularly CXXXV. <hi>Pſal. 5. 6. I know that the LORD is great, and that our LORD is above all Gods. Whatſoever the LORD pleaſed, that did he in Heaven, and in Earth, in the Sea, and all deep Places.</hi> Where as he ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects what he thinks good; ſo nothing can be effected by any Agent, unleſs he think good to permit it. For, he aws the Thoughts, and reſtrains the Paſſions, and binds the Hands, and fetters the goings of Men; ſo that they cannot move a ſtep, but as he ſuffers them. Whence that of <hi>Jacob</hi> to his Wives, <hi>your Father hath deceived me, and changed my Ways ten times: but God ſuffered him not to hurt me,</hi> XXXI. Gen. 7. That is, let him proceed no further in his Projects then to ſhow his ill Intentions towards me. And thus <hi>David</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Patriarchs, and of God's reſpect towards them, and care of them, ſaith, <hi>he ſuffered no Man to do them wrong; yea, he reproved Kings for their ſake, ſaying; Touch not mine anointed, and do my Prophets no harm,</hi> CV. Pſal. 14. 15. The greateſt Reſolution can proceed no further, the ſtrongeſt Power can effect no more then the ſupreme Governor of all will allow.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93238:8"/>
               <p>III. And as nothing comes to paſs, but what he ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther effects or permits, ſo he effects and permits nothing but for Wiſe and Holy Ends. He that is infinitely Wiſe, cannot but Exerciſe that Wiſdom in all that falls under its View; for, did he not ſo, he were not infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely Wiſe. And for the ſame Reaſon, he that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely Holy, cannot but deſign moſt Holy Ends in all the Contrivances of his Wiſdom. From whence it is, that the Holy Books aſcribe the Event of Things not meerly to his <hi>Will,</hi> but to the <hi>Counſel of his Will.</hi> For, <hi>with him is Wiſdom and Strength,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> admirably ſpeaks in the Chapter before-named, (XII. 13, 14.) <hi>he hath Counſel and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding. Behold, he breaks down, and it cannot be built up again; he ſhuts up a Man, and there can be no opening.</hi> Which he manifeſts to be true ſometimes, in ſuch ſurpriſing Ways, that the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, he is <hi>wonderful in Wiſdom, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in Working,</hi> XXVIII. 29. And <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> that he is <hi>great in Counſel, and mighty in Work,</hi> XXXII. 19. and as St. <hi>Paul</hi> Sums up this Matter, <hi>worketh all things after the Counſel of his own Will,</hi> I. Epheſ. 11.</p>
               <p>Nor doth his Wiſdom manifeſt it ſelf in his <hi>Doings</hi> only, but in his <hi>Permiſſions</hi> too: in what he ſuffers to be done, even contrary to his own Commands. The Sinner intends one thing in the Sin he commits; and God intends another, in permitting it. The Sinner to gratifie his own Luſts, his Pride, his Rage, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Covetouſneſs, or Revenge: But God to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Juſtice, his Power and Wiſdom; whereby he puniſhes, corrects, amends, improves, and perfects Men; according as they are ſeverally Qualified for his Favour or Diſpleaſure.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:93238:8"/>
               <p>Thus what <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren did to ſatisfie their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, God ſuffered for moſt excellent Purpoſes: to ſave their whole Family, in a ſore and General Famine; and to accompliſh what he ſaid to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that his Seed ſhould long ſojourn in <hi>Aegypt:</hi> And thus the Invaſion of the King of <hi>Aſſyria</hi> was permitted by God, as a Chaſtiſement of the Jews for their many and great Sins: but intended by him, to fill his Coffers by Spoil and Rapine. <hi>O Aſſyrian,</hi> ſaith the LORD by the Prophet, <hi>the Rod of my Anger, and the Staff in your Hand is my Indignation,</hi> X. Iſa. 5. Did he then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to ſerve God in this Expedition, and execute his Anger? No ſuch thing: For, thus it follows, <hi>v. 7. Howbeit, he meaneth not ſo; neither doth his Heart think ſo; but it is in his Heart to deſtroy, and to cut off Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons not a few.</hi> That is, to make all the Ravage he is able.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee that whatſoever Men deſign and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, God always deſigns ſome Juſt, Wiſe, and Holy End; in all that he effects or permits in the World.</p>
               <p>IV. And as he deſigns theſe Ends, ſo they certainly come to paſs; in deſpite of all Oppoſition, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Powers can make againſt them: <hi>For, none can ſtay his Hand, or ſay unto, what doſt thou?</hi> And as none can withſtand his Power, ſo none can avoid his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, or control his Purpoſes: For, <hi>there is no Wiſdom, nor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, nor Counſel againſt the LORD,</hi> XXI. Prov. 30. But <hi>the Counſel of the LORD,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, ſtandeth for ever; and the Thoughts of his Heart to all Generations,</hi> XXXIII. Pſal. 11. And thus it ſtandeth againſt all Oppoſition and Contrivances of Men: For, <hi>there are many Devices in Man's Heart; but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93238:9"/> the Counſel of the LORD that ſhall ſtand,</hi> XIX. Prov. 21. And all the Skill wherewith any underſtanding Creature is or can be endued, all the Devices and Projects of Mens Hearts, are as ſubject unto his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible Wiſdom, and the Counſel of his Will, as the Life, Being, and Motion of Natural Things. Which Subjection doth no way deprive them of all Liberty and Freedom, in conſulting, deviſing, and projecting: but only of Power to appoint ſuch Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs as they pleaſe, to their own Projects and Devices. And the more ample we allow the Sphaere of any Creatures Liberty to be, in deviſing and projecting; the more Admirable doth the Counſel of the moſt High appear, in directing and ordering its free Courſes, to ſuch Ends as he appoints.</p>
               <p>Now theſe Ends God accompliſhes ſometimes by <hi>common</hi> and ordinary Means: ſometimes by Means wholly <hi>Miraculous:</hi> and ſometimes by ſuch as not wholly Miraculous, but have ſomething <hi>Extraordinary</hi> in them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> Sometimes by common and ordinary Means: as when the diligent Hand getteth Riches; and Sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs and Negligence brings Men to Poverty. When the Proud and Ambitions fall into a Snare, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangles them in Deſtruction; and the Meek, the Humble, and Patient, inherit the Earth. Theſe Means commonly produce ſuch Ends; yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Succeſs from God: who ſometimes is pleaſed to hinder their Production; for Reaſons beſt known to himſelf. So the Son of <hi>Sirach</hi> hath obſerved, XI. <hi>Eecluſ. 14. Proſperity and Adverſity; Life and Death; Poverty and Riches, come of the Lord.</hi> The laſt of which he thus Explains in the foregoing Verſes; 11. 12. <hi>There
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93238:9"/> is one that laboureth and taketh pains, and maketh haſte; and is ſo much the more behind. Again, there is another that is ſlow and hath need of help, wanting Ability, and full of Poverty; yet the Eye of the Lord looketh upon him for good, and ſetteth him up from his low eſtate.</hi> In theſe common things (particularly in Ploughing, Sowing, and Harveſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) we do not attribute to God ſo much as we ought to do; and one reaſon of it is, that we either are not converſant in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or do not mind them when we read them. And <hi>the often repetition of the Words of Life</hi> (as an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Man of our own long ago obſerved) <hi>without due Reverence and Attention to them, breeds an inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility or deadneſs in mens Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>II. Which is ſo true, that though God ſometimes produces the Ends he deſigns (as I obſerved in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place) by ſuch Means as are wholly miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; yet Mens Souls continue benummed and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pified, unleſs they ſeriouſly conſider, and lay them to Heart. For, thus he often Ruled among the Stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Jews: whom he ſeems to have Choſen, to be a Theatre of his Providence; in them to give a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration unto all the Nations of the World, and to all following Generations, of his Power Ruling eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-where. Thus he delivered them out of the Hand of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> by an out-ſtretched Arm, (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks). Thus he paſſed them through the Red Sea; thus he fed and maintained them in the Wilderneſs; and at laſt brought them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> by a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Succeſſion of Wonders wrought by his mighty Power among them; that <hi>all the Ends of the Earth might fear him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93238:10"/>
               <p>III. But ſometimes he Works his Ends by a middle ſort of Means or Cauſes; ſuch as are not perfectly Miraculous, but yet have ſomething extraordinary in them.</p>
               <p>When ſecond Cauſes are not proportionable to their Effects; when they produce things unexpected, and which ſeem altogether improbable; when leſſer things prevail over greater, weaker overthrow the Strength of thoſe that ſeemed in all humane Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be far Mightier: here is ſomething that is very Extraordinary, ſomething that is Remarkable, a marvellous Hand of God; though nothing, perhaps, perfectly Miraculous. Read the Story of <hi>Eſther</hi> and <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and obſerve how they prevailed againſt the potent Intereſt, and dreadful Project of <hi>Haman,</hi> (in which the whole Empire was engaged) and you will find ſuch a Concurrence of ſtrange things, as will convince you, there was a wonderful Hand of God in it. Every one of thoſe Occurrences apart, may ſeem uſual and ordinary: as that King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> could not ſleep; and that he called for a Book to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him, rather than Inſtruments of Muſick; and that they brought the Chronicles of the Kingdom, rather than any other Book; and that they read there, where <hi>Mordecai</hi>'s good Deeds were Recorded, but had been forgotten by him; and that <hi>Haman</hi> ſhould juſt then come into the Court, when the King inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what had been done for <hi>Mordecai;</hi> and ſhould himſelf unwittingly contrive the greateſt Honour to be put upon him; and appointed to be the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it: Theſe, and all the reſt, conſidered ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally and ſingly, alone by themſelves, cannot be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93238:10"/> called Extraordinary: but take them all together, in their intire Frame and Compoſure, it is ſuch as can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be aſcribed to any but his Workmanſhip, who Created all things, by an aſtoniſhing Artifice.</p>
               <p>Thus are things that ſeem unlikely brought to paſs by the ſecret Counſel of God, againſt the moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Intereſt, Contrivances, and Combinations that can be raiſed upon Earth.</p>
               <p>And of this ſort were thoſe two great Providences of God, for which we bleſs him this Day; and are met here together to celebrate the Remembrance of them publickly, with our thankful Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> The happy Deliverance of King <hi>JAMES</hi> the Firſt, and the Three Eſtaes of this Realm, from the moſt Traiterous, and Bloody intended Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacre by Gunpowder.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The happy Arrival of his preſent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty on this Day, for the Deliverance of our Church and Nation.</p>
               <p>The former of theſe was a Deliverance ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, if it be conſidered in all its Circumſtances, that it can hardly be parallel'd in any humane Story. I will mention but theſe Two things,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>First,</hi> The Inevitableneſs of our Danger, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Humane Reaſon.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Marvellous Manner of its Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and Prevention.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93238:11"/>
               <p>I. In the former of theſe, there are two Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which ſhow the intended Deſtruction was Inevitable, if God by an extraordinary Providence had not interpoſed to prevent it.</p>
               <p>They are the Secrecy of its Contrivance; and the Perſons by whom it was Contrived and Managed.</p>
               <p>1. As to the Secrecy of the Contrivance, it was ſo great, that the Conſpirators themſelves boaſted of it, in the Letter which diſcovered all: wherein were theſe Words; <hi>They ſhall receive a terrible Blow this Parliament; and yet they ſhall not ſee who Hurts them.</hi> For, ſo ſecret was the Deſign, that though it had been long Working; yet it lay Concealed, without the leaſt Inkling of it, till within XII Hours of its in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Execution. It was a Work of Darkneſs, framed under Ground; where no Eye (but God's) could ſee them. They buried their Counſel in the Depth of the Earth; and bound themſelves like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the moſt Sacred Ties, never to diſcloſe, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or Indirectly, by Word or Circumſtance, the Matter propounded to them to keep Secret: Nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from the Execution thereof; unleſs the reſt ſhould give Leave.</p>
               <p>Thus every Man Swore that entered into this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, by the Bleſſed Trinity, and by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which then they received.</p>
               <p>2. After this it was not likely they ſhould ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diſcloſe it, or Deſiſt from it; if we conſider <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Perſons ingaged in it: who were Men of deſperate Reſolution, as well as of deſperate Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93238:11"/> They were all Inſpired with a falſe Religious Zeal; ſpurred on by a Fancy, that they were about an Action Meritorious; whereby they ſhould highly ſerve God, and his Catholick Church. Which ſo hardned their Hearts, that he who was firſt apprehended, was not ſo much as abaſht, nor expreſſed the leaſt ſign of Trouble; but only for this, that he had not done the Execution. When the reſt alſo came to Suffer for this Treaſon, they did not repent of it; nor beg Pardon: unleſs upon this Condition, that the Pope and the Church ſhould declare it a Sin. Which I do not find they have done to this Day.</p>
               <p>Now how could Men of ſuch Principles and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, relent or think of going back; when they certainly believed they were ſet on Work by God, and were warranted by his Will; and infallibly guided by his chief Miniſter, to bring the greateſt Glory to God, and to advance his Religion? Theſe and the like Advantages, made the Diſcovery of this Conſpiracy ſo unlikely; that they were fully aſſured in their own Minds of the Succeſs.</p>
               <p>II. And yet, now behold, how this Work of Darkneſs was brought to Light, even by themſelves; for, it could no other ways be Diſcovered: And that it ſhould be diſcovered by them, is little ſhort of a Miracle. For, you have heard how they were Bound by a ſolemn Oath, not to give the leaſt Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of it, <hi>Directly, or Indirectly, by Word or by Circumſtance.</hi> And yet ſo it was, that one of them, who was willing to work ſuch a Publick Miſchief, had a deſire to ſecure a private Friend from the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. And this againſt his own Intention; againſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93238:12"/> his Reſolution; againſt his Oath, as well as againſt his Intereſt: Nay, and againſt the Judgment of their Oracle (<hi>F. Garnet,</hi> the Jeſuite) who had ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led this Point in a deliberate Anſwer to this Queſtion propoſed to him; Whether the Innocent (that is, thoſe of their Religion) might be Deſtroyed with the Guilty, (that is, with thoſe of ours) when the Good that would come thereby would abundantly compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate their Loſs? Unto which he gave this Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That they might: Nay, That it would be a thing of great Merit, if thereby ſome great Benefit would be procured to the Catholiques. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all which contrary Obligations, one of them opened a little Crevice, whereby there was a way made to look into this Work of Helliſh Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>This moſt certainly was the extraordinary Hand of God; and ought to be ſo acknowledged by us. It was not extraordinary indeed, that one of them ſhould Admoniſh an honourable Friend of a Danger; unleſs it were in this, that there ſhould be ſo much good Nature left in the Breaſt of a Man, who had conſented to the Ruine of his Country. But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, this was Extraordinary, that a Man under ſuch ſacred Ties of the ſtricteſt Secrecy, ſhould give the ſmalleſt Notice of a Danger; and that he ſhould expreſs his Mind in ſuch Terms as gave Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of ſome unuſual hidden and unſeen Danger; and <hi>(Laſtly,)</hi> That the mind of the King ſhould be awakned to apprehend a Danger by ſome Blaſt of Gunpowder.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93238:12"/>
               <p>Theſe things ought to be aſcribed to that moſt watchful Providence of God, whereof I have been diſcourſing: which ſometimes in an extraordinary manner <hi>diſappoints the Devices of the Crafty; ſo that their Hands cannot perform their Enterprize.</hi> To this alone, the King and the whole Kingdom, aſcribe it in that Act of Parliament, which is appointed to be read in all Pariſh-Churches this Day: wherein they acknowledge, God was pleaſed <hi>by inſpiring the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, with a Divine Spirit, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret ſome dark Phraſes of a Letter, above and beyond all ordinary Conſtruction, miraculonſly to diſcover this hidden Treaſon, not many Hours before the appointed time for the Execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They call it <hi>Miraculous</hi> in a large Senſe; becauſe it was Extraordinary, Wonderful, and Amazing, as miraculous Events are.</p>
               <p>And therefore thoſe Proteſtants who would intitle a great Stateſman to the Diſcovery, have juſtly been thought to have a Spice of Atheiſm in their Breaſts; as a great Man obſerved, who lived in thoſe Days. They would have nothing (ſaith he) imputed to God; whoſe Hand was ſo viſible in this Diſcovery, that it could not be denied, but by aſcribing it to an Oracle of Ingelligence in thoſe times: who they ſay (without any other Authority for it, but their own) knew of this Conſpiracy long before, and let it go on; becauſe he could catch them, when he pleaſed.</p>
               <p>But as this is for private Men to give the lye to the whole Kingdom, King and all; ſo it is to rob God of the Glory of his marvellous Works: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be worſe then Heathens, who aſcribed ſuch ſtrange Events to ſome unknown God, or to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93238:13"/> Goddeſs Fortune; rather than think, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but humane Contrivance in them. Far be it for any of us to entertain ſuch a Thought; which can ſpring from nothing but an unwillingneſs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Doctrine of Providence, which <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> himſelf here Proclaims to all the World; when he ſaith, <hi>He doth according to his Will in the Army of Heaven, and among the Inhabitants of the Earth,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Nor is the Providence of God leſs apparent, in that other great Mercy, for which this Day is become Memorable, as might be ſhown in all the foregoing Particulars. But let it ſuffice to remember you in general, that when the Deſign of Deſtroying our Religion and Liberties, had been laid with great Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, and carried on with ſuch Subtilty for many Years, that our Foot was in the Snare, before we perceived that it was laid for us; when the Nation had been ſo deluded by fair Promiſes, and by their own Credulity, that the Danger wherein we were, did not appear, till we knew not how to avoid it; When our Romiſh Adverſaries had gotten ſuch an abſolute Power over us, that it imboldned them to break through all Reſtraints of Law, and every o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Obligation: Then, when we were in theſe Straits, God was pleaſed to raiſe up the Spirit of our preſent Soveraign, to enterprize our Deliverance; and with the hazard of his own Perſon, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour our Preſervation.</p>
               <p>And as nothing could Diſcourage him in this Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking (but though he was driven back by a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt at his firſt ſetting out, he calmly perſued his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93238:13"/> truſting in that Almighty Providence, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which he had committed himſelf), So he found all things in the Iſſue ſucceed much beyond all Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation. God turned the Hearts of the whole Realm to favour his Deſign ſo far, as to wiſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity to him in his Voyage hither. And he turned the Winds alſo to be ſo favourable; that if they had been abſolutely at his own Diſpoſal, he could not have commanded them to be more obſequious to him, then he found them. For, when he was brought to our Coaſt by a ſtrong Gale, in a very ſpeedy Courſe; and had over-ſhot his Port; the Wind changed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, and brought him back to his deſired Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Theſe are but a few of thoſe wonderful things, that concurred to his ſafe Landing here, on this Day eight Year, without any Oppoſition: And made him appear like an Hand out of a Cloud to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue us from our eminent Danger: being ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friended from above, that with an Handful of Men in compariſon, he ſtruck ſuch a Terror into his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that they melted before him, as the Wax be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Fire; and were ſcattered as the Duſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Wind. He was Received everywhere with the joyful Acclamations of the People: and in a ſhort time placed peaceably upon the Throne of theſe Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>Thus God daſht in a Moment, the Projects that had been forming, no body knows how many Years. Their long-laid Deſigns miſcarried on a ſudden; when they thought nothing could hinder the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. A Deliverer was ſent unexpectedly to us, when we were ready to periſh; and without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93238:14"/> of ours, we ſaw all the Contrivances of thoſe that hated us, utterly broken in pieces.</p>
               <p>This we muſt acknowledge, was brought about by the ſingular Providence of God; who, when we were left in very great Confuſion, wrought things beyond our Hopes, into the happy Settlement we now enjoy. We cannot aſcribe ſuch a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Revolution of Affairs, to meer humane Force, which was very ſmall: But to the omnipotent Hand of God, whoſe <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Ruleth over all:</hi> And who <hi>ſcattereth the Proud</hi> (as the Bleſſed Virgin ſpeaks in her Song) <hi>in the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of their Heart; putting down the Mighty from their Seats, and exalting them of low Degree,</hi> I. Luke 51. 52.</p>
               <p>Of which Doctrine great Uſe may, and ought to be made; both by them whom God hath thus won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully defeated; and by our ſelves, whom he hath preſerved from their wicked Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>To the former, another Holy Woman hath given moſt excellent Counſel, in her Song, I. <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 3. <hi>Talk no more ſo exceeding proudly, let not Arrogancy come out of your Mouth: for, the LORD is a God of Knowledge, and by him Actions are weighed. The Bows of the mighty Men are broken; and they that ſtumbled, are girt with ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we our ſelves are moſt concerned to make a right uſe of what hath been ſaid; and therefore, I ſay no more to others, but apply my ſelf to thoſe who enjoy the Benefit of theſe great Deliverances which God hath vouchſafed to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93238:14"/>
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>And <hi>First,</hi> we ſhould all learn to live in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Senſe of God, and of his over-ruling Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and accordingly in all our Affairs, whether Publick or Private, to have a regard to him, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, and to put our whole Truſt in him: conſidering that he Governs the World, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns it according to his wife Will and Pleaſure. His Eyes behold all the Concernments of the Sons of Men: Nothing comes to paſs, but what he effects or permits among them: He effects and permits nothing, but out of Wiſe, Holy, and Excellent Ends; and whatſoever Ends he abſolutely purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, thoſe he will certainly accompliſh: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all our ways, we ought, as I ſaid, to have a Reſpect unto him; and commit our ſelves and Undertakings unto the Direction of his good Providence: And above all things take care, that we be found in ſuch Courſes as he approves, and we may rationally hope he will Favour and Bleſs. For, there is not a greater Comfort in the World, than this Doctrine, if we render our ſelves ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of the Favour of his good Providence. Which is, by endeavouring that our Ways may be ſo pleaſing to God, that we may humbly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect he will ſucceed and proſper them; unleſs he intend ſome greater Good to us, by the Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That's the next Uſe we ought to make of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; to take the ſtricteſt care, that we never ſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93238:15"/> much as deſign, much leſs undertake any thing, but what we know is agreeable to God's moſt Holy Will, and upon which we may look for his Bleſſing.</p>
               <p>For, though he may permit Sinners to do Evil, and for the preſent to work their own Ends by it; yet, as this is no excuſe to thoſe Sinners, ſo it will prove no advantage to them in the Iſſue: Nay, he often daſhes all their Hopes, and ſpoils all their Projects in a Moment, when they little expect it. But if we <hi>Delight our ſelves in the LORD, and do good,</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, XXXVII. 3. 4.) <hi>he will give us the Deſires of our Heart:</hi> or make even Diſappointments to prove advantagious to us, by that good Providence, which knows how to Work all things for the good of thoſe that love him. And on the other ſide, whatſoever Miſchief wicked Men deviſe againſt us, he will either wholly put it by, or let it proceed ſo far only, as to make his Wiſdom appear in their Defeat; or let it ſucceed to produce the greateſt Good to thoſe that fear him.</p>
               <p>We muſt live therefore in the Fear and Love of God; in dutiful Obedience to our Soveraign, and to the Laws; and be juſt, and charitable, and kind one to another. For, in theſe, and ſuch like things, we are ſure we fulfil the Will of God; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may promiſe our ſelves to be favoured by his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Providence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>Unto whom we are bound to be very thankful, for the proſperous Iſſues and Events of all good Deſigns in the World, whether of our own or other
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93238:15"/> Men; and for the defeating of all wicked Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances: and more particularly thoſe wherein the publick Safety and Tranquility is concerned; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch ſingular Providences of God, as we this day Commemorate.</p>
               <p>If God demonſtrate his Providence in any thing here in this World, (and I have proved he ſhows it in all things) he exerciſes it in the Governing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending, and Protecting of publick Perſons and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties. And never was there a more viſible Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Divine Providence over a Kingdom; than in the Diſcovery and Prevention of the Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Treaſon; and in the late Defeat which he unexpectedly gave to the ſame Conſpirators againſt our Religion and Liberties. Concerning both which Deliverances, we may ſay, as the Pſalmiſt doth in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſe: <hi>They imagined a miſchievous Device, which they were not able to perform. They travelled with Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, they conceived Miſchief, and brought forth Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood. They made a Pit, and digged it, and are fallen into the Pit which they made.</hi> For, the Event of the Gunpowder Conſpiracy, by the merciful Providence of the Almighty, proved the diſcloſer of it to be a falſe Prophet, and to have ſpoken Preſumptuouſly; when he ſaid in his Letter; That <hi>God and Man had concurred to Puniſh the Iniquity of thoſe Times;</hi> by that Blow which they intended. The Blow, bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be God, fell upon themſelves; and they ſuffered the juſt Puniſhment of their own Iniquities. In the Snare which they laid, was their own Foot taken; and they fell by their own Wickedneſs: but we eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowler: the Snare was broken, and we were delivered.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93238:16"/>
               <p>So that I may ſay as King <hi>JAMES</hi> did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Occaſion, <hi>Whereas they thought to Extirpate us and our Memory; their infamous Memory ſhall by this means remain, to the End of the World. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the one part, and upon the other, God's great and merciful Deliverance of his Anointed, and of us all, ſhall remain in never-dying Records: And the ſame God grant, that it may be Engraven in Marble-Tables of Thankfulneſs in our Hearts.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>But we muſt not expreſs our Gratitude meerly in rendring Praiſe and Thankſgiving unto the Author of our Deliverances; but in the faithful Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them alſo to his Glory: by the ſincere Love and Practice of that Holy Religion, which hath been ſo often, in ſuch a marvellous manner preſerved, and ſtill is continued to us.</p>
               <p>A Religion which teaches us to Worſhip God moſt purely; and to believe all things that he hath revealed unto us; to Honour and Obey the King alſo, moſt conſcientiouſly, next to God: for, it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges no Superiour to him, in theſe his Realms and Dominions; nor will let us believe, that any body can diſpenſe with the Duty we owe him. A Religion which abhors private Conſpiracies and Rebellion, as much as it doth Hereſies and Schiſms. Which leads us in the way of the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Catholick Church of Chriſt; which doth not allow us to do any Evil, for the obtaining the greateſt Good. In ſhort, a Religion which is wholly Built upon the undoubted Word of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93238:16"/> God, and not upon the uncertain Traditions of Men.</p>
               <p>Unto this therefore let us adhear with a ſtedfaſt Affection, and unſhaken Fidelity. Let us preſerve this moſt carefully, which hath been wonderfully preſerved by God. And there is no way to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it like a ſincere Practice of that Piety which it teacheth us: In which let us endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to grow more and more; and be quickned to it by theſe <hi>Two</hi> Motives.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>First,</hi> That the Work of Reformation it ſelf, was at firſt Effected by an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Providence of God; through mean and weak Inſtruments: when many greater Perſons, who wiſht for a Reformation, thought it impoſſible to be brought about.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> That it hath been here among us, in as extraordinary a manner preſerved; by the ſame Almighty Providence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it was wrought. So our Fore-fathers have teſtified unto us, who ſaw this day which God himſelf made Memorable, by the marvellous Deliverance which he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to them. And ſo we our ſelves are able to teſtifie, who have again ſeen his Salvation upon this very day; which he hath made anew, to be a day of Praiſe to him, and Bleſſing to us.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Let us be afraid of Provoking ſo gracious and bountiful a Benefactor, by obſtinate Diſobedience to his holy Laws: which he hath bound upon us
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93238:17"/> by ſuch endearing Obligations. Let us cheerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do his Will; who hath done for us accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Hearts deſire. This was the End for which God vouchſafed ſuch wonderful Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as are Recorded in the CV. <hi>Pſalm, That they might obſerve his Statutes, and keep his Laws.</hi> So that Pſalm concludes, and the very ſame, no doubt, God expects from us: who ought to charge ourſelves with theſe <hi>Two</hi> things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> To preſerve the Memory of what God hath done for us: <hi>For, he hath ſo done his marvellous Works, that they might be had in remembrance,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks, CXI. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> To conſider, that then we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them as we ought, when we <hi>remember his Commandments to do them.</hi> Then we may have a good hope, that the LORD who <hi>hath been mindful of us, will ſtill bleſs us, he will bleſs the Houſe of Iſrael, he will bleſs the Houſe of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aron. He will bleſs them that fear the LORD, both ſmall and great,</hi> CXV. Pſal. 12. 13. For, <hi>the Mercy of the LORD is from everlaſting to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, upon them them that fear him; and his Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs unto Childrens Children. To ſuch as keep his Covenant, and to thoſe that remember his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments to do them,</hi> CIII. 17, 18.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:93238:17"/> Which the God of all Grace give us Hearts, ſincerely to Reſolve and Study, for the ſake of Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus: To whom, with the Father, and the Holy Ghost, be Glory and Majeſty, Dominion and Power, both now and ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:93238:18"/>
            <head>Books Written by <hi>SYMON PATRICK,</hi> D. D. now Lord Biſhop of <hi>ELY;</hi> and Printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Parable of the Pilgrim, written to a Friend. The 6 Edition. <hi>4to.</hi> 1681.</p>
            <p>—<hi>Menſa Myſtica:</hi> Or, a Diſcourſe concerning the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper: In which the Ends of its Inſtitution are ſo manifeſted, our Addreſſes to it ſo directed, our Behaviour there and afterward ſo compoſed, that we may not loſe the Profits which are to be received by it. With Prayers and Thankſgivings inſerted. To which is annexed</p>
            <p>—<hi>Aqua Genitalis:</hi> A Diſcourſe concerning Baptiſm: In which is inſerted a Diſcourſe to perſuade to a confirmation of the Baptiſmal Vow. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—<hi>Jewiſh</hi> Hypocriſie: A Caveat to the preſent Generation. Wherein is ſhewn both the falſe and the true way to a Nations or Perſons compleat Happineſs from the ſickneſs and recovery of the Jewiſh State. To which is added, a diſcourſe upon <hi>Micah,</hi> 6. 8. belonging to the ſame matter. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—Divine Arithmatick: A Sermon at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Samuel Jacomb,</hi> Miniſter of St. <hi>Mary-Woolneth-Church</hi> in <hi>Lombard-ſtreet, London.</hi> With an Account of his Life. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—A Sermon preached at the Funeral of Mr. <hi>Tho. Grigg,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſhaft, London. 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—An Expoſition of the Ten Commandments. <hi>8vo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—Heart's Eaſe: Or, a Remedy againſt all Troubles. With a Conſolatory Diſcourſe, particularly directed to thoſe who have loſt their Friends and Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. To which is added Two Papers, printed in the time of the late Plague. The ſixth Edition corrected. <hi>12mo.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>—The Pillar and Ground of Truth. A Treatiſe ſhewing that the Roman Church falſly claims to be <hi>That Church, and the Pillar of That Truth</hi> menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Tim. 3. 15. 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—An Examination of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Second Note of the Church, <hi>viz. A N<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITY. 4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—An Examination of the the Texts which Papiſts cite out of the Bible to prove the Supremacy of St. <hi>Peter</hi> and of the Pope over the whole Church. In Two Parts. 4to.</p>
            <p>—A private Prayer to be uſed in difficult times.</p>
            <p>—A Thankſgiving for our late wonderful Deliverance.</p>
            <p>—A Prayer for Charity, Peace and Unity; chiefly to be uſed in <hi>Lent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—A Sermon preached upon St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Day; printed with Enlargements. <hi>4to.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—A Sermon preached in St. <hi>James</hi>'s Chappel, before the Prince of <hi>Orange, Jan.</hi> 20. 1688. on <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 11. 6.</p>
            <p>—A Second Part of the Sermon before the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> on the ſame Text. Preached in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—A Sermon preached before the Queen in <hi>March</hi> 1688 / 9. on <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3. 15.</p>
            <p>—A Sermon againſt Murmuring, preached at <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> in <hi>Lent,</hi> 16 on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 10.</p>
            <p>—A Sermon againſt Cenſuring; preached at <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> in <hi>Advent;</hi> 1688. on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
            <p>—Faſt-Sermon before the King and Queen, <hi>Apr.</hi> 16. 1690. on <hi>Prov.</hi> 14. 34.</p>
            <p>—A Thankſgiving-Sermon before the Lords, <hi>Nov.</hi> 26. 1691. for reducing of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the King's ſafe Return. On <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 9.</p>
            <p>—A Faſt-Sermon before the Queen, <hi>Apr.</hi> 8. 1692. On <hi>Numb.</hi> 10. 9.</p>
            <p>—Sermon before the Lord Mayor at St. <hi>Brides</hi> Church, on <hi>Eaſter-Munday,</hi> 1696. on 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 8.</p>
            <p>—A Commentary on the Firſt Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> called <hi>Geneſes, 4to.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>—A Commentary on the Second Book of <hi>Moſes,</hi> called <hi>Exodus, 4to.</hi> 1697.</p>
            <p>—A Sermon before the Lords, <hi>Nov.</hi> 5. 1696. on <hi>Dan<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 4. 35.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:93238:18"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
